<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: frontend | Manuel van Rijn]]></title>
  <link href="http://manuel.manuelles.nl/blog/categories/frontend/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://manuel.manuelles.nl/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-20T08:13:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://manuel.manuelles.nl/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Manuel van Rijn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yeoman meets Travis CI]]></title>
    <link href="http://manuel.manuelles.nl/blog/2012/09/17/yeoman-meets-travis-ci/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-17T14:45:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://manuel.manuelles.nl/blog/2012/09/17/yeoman-meets-travis-ci</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2012/06/22/integrate-travis-ci-into-grunt/"><img class="right" src="/images/posts/yeoman-logo.png" width="200" height="200" title="Yeoman" ></a> Today I'd like to show how you can integrate Travis CI within your Yeoman project.</p>

<p><a href="http://travis-ci.org/">Travis CI</a> is a hosted continuous integration service for open source projects and <a href="http://yeoman.io">Yeoman</a> is a robust and opinionated set of tools, libraries, and a workflow that can help developers quickly build beautiful, compelling web apps.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Adding Travis CI support</h2>

<p>When Yeoman was released I've tried to add Travis CI support to a test project. After setting everything up there seemed to be a problem with the update check being fired when running tests. This was annoying because Travis CI was waiting for input from the user.</p>

<p>So I've fixed the issue and created a <a href="https://github.com/yeoman/yeoman/pull/369">pull request</a> that was merged very quick thanks to <a href="http://www.addyosmani.com">Addy Osmani</a>.</p>

<p>Anyway today I saw that there was a new version released which includes my fix and I like to share how you can make your Yeoman project be tested within Travis CI.</p>

<h3>TL;DR;</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://github.com/manuelvanrijn/yeoman-travis-ci/commit/32203d84ca2dbba2faa671e55afede8a1e6666df">this commit</a> with all the changes you have to make to your existing Yeoman project in order to get Travis CI integration.</p>

<p>Or just browse my test project here: <a href="https://github.com/manuelvanrijn/yeoman-travis-ci">yeoman-travis-ci</a></p>

<h3>package.json</h3>

<h4>Adding the yeoman dependency</h4>

<p>First we have to add the yeoman package as a dependency to our <code>package.json</code> file because we can't install yeoman globally on Travis CI.</p>

<p><code>yml
"devDependencies": {
  "yeoman": "~0.9.1"
}
</code></p>

<p>After adding the dependency and running <code>npm install</code> you'll see that yeoman is installed in the <code>node_modules</code> folder of your project.</p>

<h4>Setup npm test script</h4>

<p>Travis CI runs the <code>npm test</code> command after fetching the project and installing the dependencies. To make npm test run the Yeoman test task, we need to add the following line into our <code>package.json</code> file.</p>

<p><code>yml
"scripts": {
  "test": "node_modules/.bin/yeoman test --verbose"
}
</code></p>

<p>I've added the <code>--verbose</code> argument because I'd like to see detailed information when my tests fail, but this is an optional argument.</p>

<p>At this point you should be able to run <code>npm test</code> and see Yeoman running your tests.</p>

<h3>Add the .travis.yml file</h3>

<p>Finally we have to add a <code>.travis.yml</code> file to let Travis CI know what language our project is and on which version(s) of NodeJS it should use to test our project against (note: Yeoman requires >= 0.8).</p>

<p><code>yml
language: node_js
node_js:
  - 0.8
  - 0.9
</code></p>

<h2>Hook &amp; Push!</h2>

<p>The final step is to add the Travis CI hook to you project in GitHub and push your project.</p>

<p>Happy coding!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
